<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Works in Progress on Antranig Basman</title>
    <link>https://ponder.org.uk/wip/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Works in Progress on Antranig Basman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>amb26web@ponder.org.uk (Antranig Basman)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>amb26web@ponder.org.uk (Antranig Basman)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ponder.org.uk/wip/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Templates and weird attributes together</title>
      <link>https://ponder.org.uk/wip/2025-04-07-templates-and-weird-attributes-together/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>amb26web@ponder.org.uk (Antranig Basman)</author>
      <guid>https://ponder.org.uk/wip/2025-04-07-templates-and-weird-attributes-together/</guid>
      <description>Trying to put into practice thoughts from the previous two postings on template thinking and weird attributes for event binding revealed some interesting problems.&#xA;Firing up ${ }-based templates revealed an awkward problem. This prevents us using backtick template literals in code since these automatically interpret ${} syntax and so will break as soon as they are evaluated.&#xA;At the same time, use of @click style event binding revealed a really interesting limitation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Staring at the wand</title>
      <link>https://ponder.org.uk/wip/2025-04-04-staring-at-the-wand/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>amb26web@ponder.org.uk (Antranig Basman)</author>
      <guid>https://ponder.org.uk/wip/2025-04-04-staring-at-the-wand/</guid>
      <description>OK, so we have now imported a visually reasonable and properly lithified version of Pell into a tiny static page which is itself lithified from the rendered output of the substrates page, which will be where the most basic editing demo gets scaffolded.&#xA;I mused about making the disclosing tool into a pencil of the kind we see in the Lively Kernel UI but the &amp;ldquo;magic wand&amp;rdquo; was hard to resist and fits in with some rhetoric about this gesture.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Change of Tack on Templating</title>
      <link>https://ponder.org.uk/wip/2025-04-03-change-of-tack-on-templating/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>amb26web@ponder.org.uk (Antranig Basman)</author>
      <guid>https://ponder.org.uk/wip/2025-04-03-change-of-tack-on-templating/</guid>
      <description>I get to staring at the markup templates that were already implemented for the Galiano 2023 Bioblitz and thinking how to adapt/reuse them for the upcoming Diatoms of the Salish Sea viz forces me to put some things in focus about how templating is going to have to work for these communities. I&amp;rsquo;d vaguely hoped that the details of how Infusion templating was going to interact with Hugo templating would somehow just &amp;ldquo;come out in the wash&amp;rdquo; but naturally this isn&amp;rsquo;t going to happen without some kind of focused plan!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hunting rich editors</title>
      <link>https://ponder.org.uk/wip/2025-03-28-hunting-rich-editors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>amb26web@ponder.org.uk (Antranig Basman)</author>
      <guid>https://ponder.org.uk/wip/2025-03-28-hunting-rich-editors/</guid>
      <description>The substrate&amp;rsquo;s transition to editability will need to present a &amp;ldquo;mostly rendered&amp;rdquo; view of itself – managed by some form of rich text editor. A huge &amp;ldquo;grab-bag list&amp;rdquo; is at JefMari&amp;rsquo;s curated list of Awesome Wysiwyg Editors which can rapidly be whittled down to a shortlist. CKEditor 5 and TinyMCE are familiar from decades ago. But the gold standard is clearly Marijn&amp;rsquo;s ProseMirror – basic example here and really nice markdown editing example here.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
